We all want to live life to the
fullest and longest, right?
Well, this video will look
at the lifestyle factors
that may enable us to do
just that. Check it out.
"How to Increase Your Life
Expectancy 12 to 14 years"
A pivotal paper published in
Europe more than a decade ago
entitled “Healthy Living Is
the Best Revenge” found that
adhering to just four simple
healthy lifestyle factors
compared to none could
potentially have a strong impact
on the prevention
of chronic diseases;
we’re talking nearly 80 percent
less chronic disease risk,
slashing diabetes
risk by 93 percent,
dropping heart attack
risk by 81 percent,
and cutting stroke risk in half,
and cancer by 36 percent.
Think about what that means.
The potential for preventing
disease and death is enormous.
In the U.S. alone every year,
there are  half million
heart attacks, half million
strokes, a million new cases
of diabetes, and a
million new cancer diagnoses.
The message is clear:
adopting a few healthy behaviors
can have a major impact.
What are those four fabled factors?
Never smoking, not being obese,
averaging about a half hour of
exercise a day, and adhering to
healthy dietary principles,
like lots of fruits, vegetables,
and whole grains, and less meat.
Follow those four
simple rules and boom!
Enjoy nearly 80 percent reduced
risk of major chronic diseases.
What does that mean
for mortality risk?
A similar batch of four healthy
behaviors combined predicted
a four-fold difference
in total mortality,
with an estimated impact
equivalent to 14 years
in chronological age, meaning
the individuals were dying at
such a reduced rate that it was
as if they were 14 years younger.
“Finally, a Regimen to
Extend Human Life Expectancy.”
This commentary was in
reference to this study,
where a similar analysis
of the impact of healthy
lifestyle behaviors on
life expectancies was made,
but this time it looked
directly at the U.S. population,
which is particularly important,
since Americans have a
shorter life expectancy
compared with residents
of nearly all other
high-income countries.
The researchers concluded that
adopting a healthy lifestyle
could substantially
reduce premature mortality
and prolong life
expectancy in U.S. adults.
Okay, but by how much?
They estimated that adherence
to a low-risk lifestyle
could prolong life expectancy
at age 50 by 14 years
in women and 12.2 years in men.
So, if you’re 50 right now,
instead of only living to 79
if you’re a woman, and
75½ if you’re a man,
taking even just basic care
of yourself could propel you
to an average life expectancy
of 93 if you’re a woman
and 87½ if you’re a man.
The bottom line is it’s never
too late to turn back the clock.
A midlife switch just
to the basics, like at least
five servings fruits
and vegetables a day,
walking even like 20 minutes a day,
maintaining a healthy
weight, and not smoking
results in a substantial
reduction in mortality
even in the following few years.
We’re talking a 40 percent
lower risk of dying
in the subsequent four years.
So, making the necessary
changes to adhere to a healthy
lifestyle could be considered
extremely worthwhile,
and middle age is certainly
not too late to act.
As an aside, realizing the
12 to 14 years of added life
study was based on data
from health professionals,
that got me excited about
all the potential knock-on effects.
If health professionals
start getting healthier,
they could become role models
for more healthful living
and potentially save more
lives than just their own.
But that may have just
been wishful thinking.
Practicing what you preach
can sometimes backfire.
Evidently, “displays of excellence
can paradoxically turn off
the very people they
are trying to inspire.”
You’d assume that not
being a hypocrite and trying
to walk the walk would just
lead to positive consequences,
inspiring confidence in others, right?
Don’t you want a dance instructor
who can dance, a music teacher
who can play, a health
professional who’s healthy?
But this simple intuition
fails to take into account
concerns about making
other people feel inadequate.
Like you know how vegetarians
are the targets of a
surprising amount of
hostility and ridicule.
That’s because they may
come off as morally superior
and make people feel like
they’re being looked down upon.
There was an elegant
demonstration of this phenomenon
in this study where
“Principled deviants who take
the high road threaten
others’ moral self-worth.”
This is what they did.
Research subjects were asked
to complete a racist
task by an experimenter,
and those moral rebels who
refused to obey were cheered
by observers but were
disparaged by participants
who had themselves
gone through with it,
and for whom the rebel’s stance
thus implied an indictment
of their spinelessness.
Isn’t that interesting?
So, when doctors portray themselves
as “the picture of health,”
patients might think they’re
being holier-than-thou and
unintentionally alienate people,
potentially turning off
the very patients who
most need their help.
You can see how someone with
a weight issue might feel
threatened and judged
by a physician triathlete.
But what are we supposed to do?
We want healthy practitioners.
Physicians who
smoke are less likely
to tell their patients
to quit smoking,
physicians who are overweight
are less likely to counsel
their patients about weight,
and physicians
who don’t work out
are less likely to
talk about exercise.
What we can do to make
patients more comfortable
is emphasize that our
role is to help people
meet their own personal health
goals, whatever they may be.
Studies show that when doctors
do this, take this approach,
it increases the appeal of
fitness-focused physicians
to overweight patients.
So, we can then display
exemplary behavior
while at the same time
not inadvertently alienate
the very people who could
benefit most from our guidance.